Today's דף daf is מ"ט, mem-tet, 49, and we are pretty much
where we need to be. We start on the משנה mishna on
מ"ח עמוד ב'. mem-chet amud bet. So let's pick up there.
The משנה mishna says as follows: we're dealing again, of course, with
questions about בכור, bechor, and we sort of moved from the question
about בכור bechor for inheritance and talking about focusing just on the
בכור bechor for the פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, but questions about identifying
who is the correct בכור. bechor. So we pick up with the
משנה. mishna.
שתי נשים שלא בכרו, shtei nashim shelo bichru, two women that have
not yet had a child, and they're both married to the same
man.
So each child, if each of them has a first son, there'll
be two פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. Let's see what happens.
ילדו שני זכרים, yaldu sheni zacharim, there were two male sons, one
for each wife, so there's going to be two פדיון הבן. pidyon
haben. נותן עשרה סלעים לכהן, noten asara sela'im l'kohen, so you give
ten סלעים sela'im to a כהן. kohen. A סלע sela is a
שקל. shekel. Fine. Now, מת אחד מהן בתוך שלושים יום, met echad
mehen betoch shloshim yom, we're always dealing with tragedy here because it
makes for interesting legal law. So if, God forbid, one of them
dies within thirty days, and the מצוה mitzvah of פדיון הבן pidyon
haben does not begin until the thirtieth day, right? It says ופדויו
מבן חודש תפדה. ufduyav miben chodesh tifdeh. Now we're going to find
out later, I mean the משנה mishna here assumes that you could
give the money before day thirty and it would still be valid.
We'll talk about the exact parameters about that later. But let's... yes?
Yesterday polygamy was pretty standard?
I don't know if it was standard or it was just used
as an interesting example. Basically what you do find out when you
learn יבמות Yevamos is that in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael it was
particularly frowned upon, and in בבל Bavel it was accepted. Although even
if it was accepted, it's not clear how prevalent it was. Even
in societies where it was accepted, you usually, often the husband had
to be pretty well off financially in order to afford more than
one wife and those children. Right, but in בבל Bavel it was
definitely more accepted than it was in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. The
משנה mishna is being written in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, so I
don't know if giving the example is, you know, it just might
be because since הלכה halacha accepts polygamy, it provides for interesting, you
know, theoretical discussion.
I read a very funny financial geographic I read recently, I'm sorry.
So this author that went through, you know, did a whole thing
about, you know, West African cultures. So, yeah, he goes to the
chief and she says, 'Oh, yeah, do you do this, do you
do that? You know, can you... do you need a... do you
need a girl to marry?' 'No, it's okay, I have a wife.'
He says, 'Do you need another?' Right. It's true.
This is really... okay. So, all right. So now, okay, so now
one of them dies, מת אחד מהן בתוך שלושים יום, met echad
mehen betoch shloshim yom, within thirty days. So again, he gave the
money before day thirty, one of these two boys died, so now
he's חייב chayav in one פדיון. pidyon. So what happens? So אם
לכהן אחד נתן, im l'kohen echad natan,
if he gave both פדיון הבן pidyon haben to the same כהן,
kohen, יחזיר לו חמישה סלעים, yachzir lo chamisha sela'im, give him back
five because now only one child is obligated. ואם לשני כהנים נתן,
v'im lishnei kohanim natan, if he gave to two separate כהנים, kohanim,
and presumably you didn't specify which was for which
child, okay, or... so therefore who are you going to get it
back from? So אינו יכול להוציא מידם, eino yachol l'hotzi miyadam, you
can't get it back from either כהן kohen because either כהן kohen
will say, 'I'm assuming it was for the other child.' Okay. זכר
ונקבה או שני זכרים ונקבה, zachar unekeiva o sheni zacharim unekeiva, if
the each mother gave... the mothers gave birth to a boy and
a girl or two boys and a girl, and you don't know
whose is whose child, okay? So in that case, you could be
you have two פדיונות pidyonot you have to do if each mother
gave birth to a boy first, or it could be that there's
only one if one of the mothers gave birth to a girl
first. So in that case, נותן חמישה סלעים לכהן, noten chamisha sela'im
l'kohen, you only give five סלעים sela'im to a כהן, kohen, five
שקל, shekel, and you say this is for whichever boy is the
first is the first. Now, שתי נקבות וזכר או שני זכרים ושתי
נקבות, shtei nekeivot v'zachar o sheni zacharim ushtei nekeivot, if there are
two girls and either one or two boys, then it's possible that
you have no firstborns. It's possible that each again there's a confusion
who, you know, who gave birth to which and what order they
gave birth. So in that case, it's possible there's no firstborns, it's
possible each woman gave birth first to a girl, and therefore you
don't give any פדיון הבן. pidyon haben.
So in that case, אין כאן לכהן כלום, ein kan l'kohen klum,
you don't give anything to a כהן. kohen. Again, notice that it's
all based on the principles of המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero
alav haraya, that if it were a civil case, since the כהן
kohen can't prove you owe him any money, you don't give. And
there's never the sense, 'Well, yeah, but I want to make sure
I'm doing my מצוה mitzvah of פדיון הבן.' pidyon haben. No, you
don't have to be concerned about that. The מצוה's mitzvah totally is
a function of whether there could be a civil liability on the
basis of it. Okay, so that's the case when there's doubt. Now,
אחת בכרה ואחת שלא בכרה, achat bichra v'achat shelo bichra, or at
least two wives, both of whom have not yet had kids yet.
Now, אחת בכרה ואחת שלא בכרה, achat bichra v'achat shelo bichra, you
have two wives, a man has two wives, one has had children
before and one has not.
And there's also going to be a confusion of whose whose child,
right? They're all born in a cave, it's dark, you don't see,
okay. ילדו שני זכרים, yaldu sheni zacharim, and there are two males.
So okay, even though you don't know whose is whose, you still
know the one without kids gave birth to a male first, and
therefore there's definitely one פדיון. pidyon. פדיון הבן pidyon haben going on
here. נותן חמש סלעים לכהן. Noten chamesh sela’im lakohen. You give five
sela’im to the kohen for whoever it happens is the firstborn. מת
אחד מהם בתוך שלושים יום. Met echad mehem betoch sheloshim yom. One
dies within 30 days, so now it turns out that one of
them is not that that that one, you know, obviously is not
obligated in פדיון הבן pidyon haben and that one might have been
the firstborn son. So in that case, you can get your money
back from the kohen. So בתוך שלושים יום האב פטור. betoch sheloshim
yom ha'av patur.
So the father is exempt and presumably if the money was given
to a kohen he can get it back. Now מת האב והבנים
קיימים, met ha’av vehabbanim kayyamim, so this is similar to what we
said before, the father died and the children are around. Now, nobody
the children didn’t die, the father died. Now, but each son says
maybe I’m not the firstborn, so I’m not going to be פודה
podeh my- give a פדיון הבן pidyon haben to the other guy
says but of course when it comes time for getting a double
portion they’ll tell a different story. Okay.
Well first of all it might be a case of לאו למה
הוא קרי lo lamma hu k'ru so then nobody is going to
get it anyway and even if they would they wouldn't be believed
unless they were קוצה דפרשה kotza d’parsha etcetera but anyway we’re not
dealing with that right now. We’re not dealing with that right now.
So right now when it’s for פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, he’s sort
of saying I’m not the firstborn I don’t have to be פודה
podeh myself. So what’s the story? So רבי מאיר אומר אם נתנו
עד שלא חלקו Rabbi Meir omer im natnu ad shello chilaku this
is just like the previous משנה. mishna. If they’ve given already they
paid before they divided the estate and now they divide it and
now each one wants to claim it back. So too bad, נתנו
natnu you’ve already given the money, you can’t get it back. The
kohen is entitled to it, you know, once you’ve given it. ואם
לאו Ve’im lav but if they haven’t given and the estate is
divided פטורים paturim they’re exempt. If you’ll remember the גמרא Gemara had
the case was that it was already 30 days before the father
died, so there was a lien on the estate and therefore but
the estate had this is the whole discussion yesterday, the estate had
exactly five shekel and therefore since you cannot collect fully from each
son you can only collect half because of various reasons about liens
and so on you would not be collecting the full five shekel.
That’s how the גמרא Gemara understood the case according to רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. But if the estate hadn’t been divided you could collect
the full five shekel. רבי יהודה אומר נתחייבו הנכסים Rabbi Yehuda omer
nitchayyuven nechasim no there’s a lien on the estate and even after
it’s been divided between the sons you can collect the full five
shekel even if it’s split between the two sons. Okay so that
was what we discussed yesterday we’re not going to re-unpack that now.
זכר ונקבה אין לכהן כלום. Zachar unekeivah ein lakohen kelum. If it’s
a boy and a girl and you don’t know who gave birth
to whom, so maybe the one who had already had children gave
birth to the boy and the one who had not had children
gave birth to the girl so there’s no one who’s obligated in
פדיון, pidyon, the kohen gets nothing. Now שתי נשים של שני אנשים
שלא בכרו, shtei nashim shel shenei anashim shello bicharu, two wives of
two men, you know, there’s, you know, I don’t know, Reuven and
Sarah and Shimon and Leah. I’m going to get confused. There’s Avraham
and
Sarah and Yitzchak and Rivka. Thank you very much. Okay. Now
שלא בכרו, shello bicharu, now neither of them have had children yet.
ילדו שני זכרים Yaldu shenei zecharim and they each had a child
fine so there’s going to be two פדיון הבן pidyon haben going
on here but the sons got mixed up. So however they worked
out who’s going to take which kid home from the hospital,
each father knows they’re obligated in פדיון pidyon whether this is their
son or the other guy’s son doesn’t- okay but I’m still obligated
in פדיון pidyon because my wife had a baby boy. So זה
נותן חמש סלעים וזה נותן חמש סלעים zeh noten chamesh sela'im vezeh
noten chamesh sela'im each one gives five sela. מת אחד מהם בתוך
שלושים יום Met echad mehem betoch sheloshim yom one died within 30
days. One of the fathers? No, one of the children. Okay so
therefore the father that child is not obligated in פדיון pidyon but
you don’t know who is the father of the child, right? Because
because you don’t know whose is whose son. So אם לכהן אחד
נתנו im lakohen echad natnu if they both gave to the same
kohen יחזיר להם חמש סלעים yachzir lahem chamesh sela’im he has to
give back because he knows this one kohen knows he has to
give back five. Now the question is fine he has to give
back five but to which father? And either father that comes to
him he’ll say maybe you’re not the father. So how are the
fathers going to be able to demand it back from him? So
here if you remember a day or two ago the גמרא Gemara
says oh we said that we’re talking about a power of attorney.
So I’m going to jump ahead but this is what we’re going
to say is that this is a case of power of attorney.
That the fathers one father gave his power of attorney to the
other father so that father’s able to now demand from the kohen
and say you either owe me or the other guy and I
have the other guy’s power of attorney and the kohen knows he
has to give back five shekel because he’s not entitled to ten
and therefore he gives back five and the two fathers split it.
Okay. Yes.
If there were no power of attorney was there any ruling like
it had to be given to tzedakah? That’s exactly I was going
to ask.
Nope. What can I tell you the answer is no. If you
can’t- you are right that in the sense like okay nobody can
demand the money from me but I’m not entitled to
it but anyway yes but there is not- there is not that
הלכה. halakha.
Sometimes the גמרא Gemara does speak
about like somebody’s coming לצאת ידי שמים latzet yedei shamayim that even
though nobody can- if he knows he owes money to one of
a couple people but- but let’s say three people come and say
you owe us a hundred dollars and he knows that he owes
one of them but he doesn’t know which one. So whatever the
scenario is and let’s say they can’t demand it from him sometimes
the גמרא Gemara does say not give the money to charity but
put the money between the people and leave like let them fight
it out. Okay. So how exactly that works, well, whatever. Anyway, so
sometimes the גמרא Gemara does discuss scenarios of לצאת ידי שמים. latzeit
yedei shamayim. If you know that you're not entitled to that money
and you want to satisfy your moral obligation, even though you can't
be sued for that money. Okay, it's never about charity, it's about
how to maybe give them the money to fight over. That is
discussed under certain scenarios. Not here. Okay, because we have other things
to discuss here. Okay, so anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara goes
on. When we're learning בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, those cases which discuss
those scenarios, we can bring this into the conversation. So make a
mental note when we come back to בבא מציעא Bava Metzia where
those where that's discussed. Anyway, so let's take a look.
So,
anyway, he's a כהן Kohen has to give back five סלע sela
and we're going to say it's a case of power of attorney.
Now,
where are we? חמש סלעים אם לשני כהנים נתנו. chamesh sela'im im
lishnei kohanim natnu. However, if it's two separate כהנים, kohanim, אין יכולים
להוציא מידם. ein yecholim lehotzi miyadam. Each כהן Kohen will say, I'm
assuming you gave me the five סלע sela for the other kid.
Since you didn't know which was your son when you gave me
the five שקל, shekel, I'm going to assume it was for the
boy who survived, not the one who died. What?
Not from the one who took home?
No, because that might not be your actual biological son. So when
you gave the five שקל, shekel, you were giving it for whichever
of those boys was your son, but you didn't know which one
it was. Now that one of them is dead, I'm going to
assume that you gave me the five שקל shekel for the one
that survived, and therefore you can't prove it's the other way. You
yourself didn't know. And therefore I don't have to return the money.
Okay.
Now, זכר ונקבה, zachar unekeivah,
let's say a boy and a girl, and again, you don't know
who's who. So האבות פטורים, ha'avot peturim, the fathers are exempt, because
each father, although there is one son that's חייב chayav in פדיון
הבן, pidyon haben, nobody knows that it's his son. Right? It might
be the other person's son. And therefore they don't have to do
a פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. Now the son knows that he's חייב.
chayav. He doesn't know who his father is, but he knows he's
חייב. chayav. So in that case הבן חייב לפדות את עצמו. haben
chayav lifdot et atzmo. He has to redeem himself when he gets
to be בר מצוה. bar mitzvah. שתי נקבות וזכר שתי
נקבות ושתי זכרים פטור. shtei nekeivot vezachar shtei nekeivot ushtei zacharim patur.
Two girls and one or two boys. It's possible that there's no
firstborn boy. It's possible that each of the mothers gave birth to
a girl first. So in that case אין לכהן כלום, ein lakohen
klum, the כהן Kohen gets nothing, the fathers don't give, the sons
don't give, because the sons themselves could say we might not be
the firstborn. Okay. אחת בכור ואחת שלא בכור או ששתיהן נשים. achat
bechor veachat shelo bechor o sheshteihen nashim. Now, you again, you have
two wives of two different husbands, but one of them has already
had children before and one has not. ילדו שני זכרים, yaldu shenei
zacharim, and they gave birth to two boys. So again, the one,
the boy of the one that has not had children before is
חייב chayav in פדיון. pidyon. But the kids got mixed up, you
don't know who's who. It still doesn't matter though, the father, the
husband of the woman who had not had kids before is חייב
chayav in פדיון הבן pidyon haben even though he doesn't know who's
his son. He does know that he has a firstborn son. זה
שלא בכרה אשתו נותן חמש סלעים לכהן. ze shelo becherah ishto noten
chamesh sela'im lakohen. The one that whose wife had never had birth
before gives five סלע sela to כהן. Kohen. He knows he has
a firstborn son. And
you know, and the other one obviously doesn't. זכר ונקבה, zachar unekeivah,
if it's a boy and a girl and you don't know who
gave birth to who. So the one whose wife had not had
kids before might have had the girl first. And there might not
be any פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. אין לכהן כלום, ein lakohen klum,
the כהן Kohen gets nothing. And we didn't bother there spelling out
yet again all the cases of what if one of them died
and so on, etc. Okay, so that seems a little bit like
we could have figured some of that out ourselves, but you get
the basic point.
Yes, so you mentioned if there's a confusion and neither child knows
whether he's required to do פדיון הבן pidyon haben and the father
died and they both reach thirteen, what do they do?
Then they don't have to give, since the כהנים kohanim can't prove
which one of them is obligated, therefore since there can't be a
civil suit, they don't have to do the מצוה mitzvah either. And
that's again, the I think the most interesting thing about all these
pages is that the מצוה mitzvah of פדיון הבן pidyon haben is
a function of the debt of פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. And if
the debt cannot be sued for, then you don't say, yeah, but
for the sake of the מצוה. mitzvah. Now I should even point
out that there's a way to do the מצוה mitzvah without having
to cause you any loss of money. You know why? Because actually
there's a גמרא Gemara that says that if you do the מצוה
mitzvah of מתנה על מנת להחזיר, matanah al menat lehachzir, you fulfill
the מצוה mitzvah of פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. Now, some say that's
the מצוה mitzvah of פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, that's not the debt
of פדיון הבן, pidyon haben, that there are two things. But let's
say you give the five שקל shekel to the כהן Kohen and
here it is as a gift on the condition you give it
back to me. So you would think that's crazy, you would think
you have to actually, you know, actually pay the money, it's like
a debt, it's not an act of giving. But there's actually a
גמרא Gemara that says that that actually works. So based on that,
you know, there's a distinction made between the debt of פדיון הבן,
pidyon haben, clearly here we're talking all about civil cases, and the
מצוה, mitzvah, the act of giving. Of course, if you make that
distinction, then you should say that in these cases, even if he
can't sue me, right, and even if he can't prove that I
owe him the money, I should give him it מתנה על מנת
להחזיר matanah al menat lehachzir just in order to do the מצוה
mitzvah and to play it safe. And here we're finding that that's
not the case, that there's no obligation even to do the ritual
act, even if you could in theory get the money back, once
there is not an underlying debt. That without that debt, there's no
מצוה, mitzvah, there's no obligation, which is I think the most fascinating
thing of
all. Right. So the point is is that you can make different
you can make different claims in different court cases, right? If the
כהן kohen wants the money I'd say I'm assuming I'm not the
בכור. bechor. What if I'm trying to collect my double portion I'm
going to assume that I am. Now none of those cases can
you prove it. The only way you can deal with it is
you can do this power of attorney. You get together with the
other, you know, with the other one, the possible בכור bechor and
you write some power of attorney, so therefore between the two of
you one of you is able to sue for the firstborn status.
But yes, you would make different claims based on what you know
what was most advantageous to you in the given court case. Yes,
Charlene?
Well if your father dies insolvent?
Yes.
Right. Right, there are cases where it doesn't pay, yes.
Is there a double portion
of debts?
No. No, yes.
Now just I know what we're talking about but nobody seems to
care very much that a father and a mother lost a child.
You know, we can't, it's not yes. When when we're dealing with
these as legal cases we have to be dispassionate to deal with
like, you know, to figure out right now the conversation is: what
are the technical parameters of the מצווה mitzvah of בכור? bechor? You
know, when you're dealing with pastoral counseling or when you're dealing with
הלכות אבילות hilchos aveilus or when you're dealing with other things, you
know, we'll deal with those, but right.
It seems so mercenary here though.
I know but you can't, but you do need to, you know,
you do need to give to treat things within their own discipline,
you know? And the technical details just are the same way.
Yes. All right.
Let's let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara. מאי שנא שני
כהנים? mai shna shnei kohanim? So why in the case of two
כהנים kohanim when you know when when you gave to two כהנים
kohanim and now you're entitled to get back from one? I mean
you whatever somebody because God forbid the son died with one of
the sons died within thirty days but you can't get back from
either כהן kohen because you don't know which one has to give
you the money back. דאזל לגבי האי ומדחי ליה ואזל לגבי האי
ומדחי ליה. de-azal legabei hai u-medachi lei ve-azal legabei hai u-medachi lei.
You go to one כהן kohen and he pushes you off and
go to the other one and he pushes you off. הכא נמי
hacha nami so even if it's a case of one כהן kohen
so when there are two different fathers and they're entitled to five
שקל shekel back
but they don't know
which father is entitled. So why does that work? Right? This is
the question we asked. ליזיל לגבי האי ולדחי וליזיל לגבי האי ולדחי.
leizeil legabei hai u-lidchi u-leizeil legabei hai u-lidchi. Why doesn't he push
off each father? He says you can't collect from me, maybe it's
the other father. I owe, yes, I got to give back five
שקל, shekel, but I don't know which father I owe it to.
So אמר שמואל amar Shmuel so שמואל Shmuel says בבר הרשאה. be-bar
harsha'ah. So this is what we referred to before. Here where the
כהן kohen definitely has to give back five, it's just a question
which father, you can say that the fathers, one of them gave
a power of attorney to the other. So one father says you
either owe me or you owe the or you owe the other
father who gave me his power of attorney, so you got to
give me five שקל shekel either way. Okay. Now that we mentioned
this idea of power of attorney, we bring in a discussion from
בבא קמא Bava Kamma about the parameters of power of attorney because
nobody ever asked how does where does this, you know, sort of
instrument of power of attorney come in הלכה? halacha? How are you
able to give over power of attorney? Now you might think what's
the big deal? I mean we know about it in secular law
but the problem is that הלכה halacha much more likes concrete things
than abstract things. It's so therefore to able to sort of make
you me and give you my power of attorney is a challenging
concept for הלכה halacha and primarily the way it does it is
by saying: anywhere that I have money that's owed to me, I
to some degree am transferring those rights to you. So you're actually
transferring an object, not just abstractly giving somebody power of attorney, but
you are transferring the ownership of those properties out there that other
people have that are owed to me. Because that is the somewhat
of the construct of power of attorney, there are some limits on
it and that's what we're going to talk about now. ואמרי נהרדעי
ve-amrei Nehardei and doesn't נהרדעי Nehardei say לא כתבינן אדרכתא? lo katvinan
adrachta? אדרכתא adrachta is another word for הרשאה, harsha'ah, it's an Aramaic
word. We don't write a power of attorney א-מטלטלי a-metalteli
on chattel, we only write it on real estate. Why? Because of
this reason. If somebody owes me is on my land, for example,
and I can't somehow bring him to court and I know you'll
have the ability to do it better than me or there's some
degree of a ספק safek like this, then I can say I'm
transferring the ownership of that land to you because real estate is
always, you know,
accessible and always considered under the control of the owner even if
somebody else is sitting on it. But if it's chattel, because chattel
can be hidden away and you know moved and taken and whatever,
if somebody else, let's say a case of a גניבה. gneivah. If
a גנב ganav is on my land, I'm still considered to be
in control of my land because it's right there. But if a
גנב ganav has taken over has taken my car and driven it
away or taken my wallet and taken it away, I can't sell
it, I can't sanctify it, it's out of my control, okay? That's
the very nature of chattel. So how can you transfer power of
attorney on chattel since the very object that you're trying to get
back is out of your control and you can't transfer ownership on
it? Is that clear? 'Cause if the concept of power of attorney
is through some type of transfer of title, you can't do a
transfer title on chattel that is out of your control. So how
you gonna do it? This is chattel, this isn't land, it's five
שקל. shekel. So the גמרא Gemara says, הני מילי היכא דכפרי. hani
mili heicha dechafrei. That's when the other person is denying that he
owes you the money. So if he's under his physical control and
he's denying that it's yours, then you have no—you're not considered to
have any access to it and any ability to transfer the rights
to it. אבל היכא דלא כפרי, aval heicha delo kafrei, the כהן
Kohein admits he owes five שקל. shekel. He just doesn't know who
he owes the five שקל shekel to, but he's not denying that
he owes one of you the money. So since he's not denying
that you owe it, then even though it is chattel, מקנינן, makninan,
you can still transfer the rights to it. So this guy admits
that he might owe me the money, he doesn't know if it's
me or the other guy, but he admits he owes somebody the
money. In case it's me he owes the money to, so therefore
the fact that he's holding on to it doesn't mean it's not
under my control. Therefore, it's enough—it's considered conceptually accessible to me that
I am enough in control that I can transfer the right to
you and empower you as power of attorney. Now, that is what
this גמרא Gemara says. However, תוספות Tosafot says here, and there's a
huge תוספות Tosafot in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, that in practice they
would be—obviously for, you know, for real-world purposes they had to be
able to write—they had to be able to write power of attorney
even when the person was denying the debt and even on chattel.
So they basically wound up saying, you know, in the period of
the גאונים Geonim and the ראשונים, Rishonim, expanding the limits of the
גמרא Gemara and saying that you could do power of attorney, you
know, even in other cases. That's a general issue, you know, which
is a whole conversation in itself, that in the דיני ממונות, Dinei
Mamonot, as, you know, sort of secular society and the economic realities
continue to evolve, how the categories in the גמרא Gemara had to
expand and adapt appropriately. So תוספות Tosafot tries to figure out why
it is that we're able to move beyond the parameters of the
גמרא, Gemara, but nevertheless that is actually what happens. Another good example,
but totally parenthetical, of הלכה's Halacha normal reluctance to deal with abstract,
you know,
sort of entities, first of all is there's no הלכתי Halachic concept
of corporation. There's only הלכה Halacha of partnership, which can be fifty
percent owners in an object. But to have an abstract corporation, so
how would הלכה Halacha deal with it? הלכה, Halacha, there's no precedent
in הלכה. Halacha. Or for example, there's no precedent in הלכה Halacha
for—intellectual property. It's not a physical thing. To have rights to intellectual
property, all of those things are areas where, you know, הלכה Halacha
works very concretely, but society moves to a point where it needs
more of these abstract entities. So—and, you know, how that gap is
bridged post the גמרא, Gemara, you know, is a challenging area in
itself. Okay. Yes.
Question: If somebody has a house,
on
the property in question, does that mean that the transfer includes the
house?
No. I can only transfer what's mine. So if—if my claim—if you
built a house on this plot and you said it was a
vacant plot, and I say no, no, actually it's mine, but I'm—I'm
having a hard time proving it. Yes.
I'm saying let's say a person owns property with a house on
it, lives in the house. Yes.
The house is considered like real estate.
So that would then—yes.
Yes. But the furniture and all of the—and all the things in
the house are not real estate, but the house is. Okay. So
now wrapping this up, this משנה, Mishnah, זכר ונקבה אין כאן לכהן
כלום. zachar u-nekeivah ein kan lacohein klum.
If it's a male and a female, then the כהן Kohein gets
nothing because then again you don't know who—maybe there was no firstborn.
So the גמרא Gemara says, תנא רב הונא, tana Rav Huna, זכר
ונקבה אין כאן לכהן כלום. zachar u-nekeivah ein kan lacohein klum. So
he also has the case
about—I'm trying to remember which case in the משנה Mishnah this was,
hold
on, let me just check רש"י. Rashi. Two
women, two different wives of two different men. So, oh, that was—remember
the end, the last case of the משנה, Mishnah, the משנה Mishnah
wrapped it up very quickly, right? So we all just thought that
it was figured that it had given enough—spun out enough detail. So
the only example we have at the end of the משנה Mishnah
where the כהן Kohein doesn't get anything of the two separate wives
is a boy and a girl and you don't know who's who,
and one of the wives has already had a first child, so
therefore it could be that the one who hasn't had had the
girl. Fine. So רב הונא Rav Huna came along and he just
fleshed out the other possibilities where the כהן Kohein would get nothing.
שני זכרים ונקבה אין כאן לכהן כלום. shenei zacharim u-nekeivah ein kan
lacohein klum. He also said two boys and a girl. It's possible
the כהן Kohein gets nothing because it's possible the two boys were
born as twins to the mother who had already had children and
the girl was to the mother who had—or it doesn't really matter,
but at least the girl was the first child to the mother
who didn't have children. So he just adds that to the משנה
Mishnah to flesh it out. ותנא דידן, v'tana didan, the author of
our משנה, Mishnah, why did he not have that case in the
end? כיון דבשתי נשים הוא דמשכחת לה. keivan de-vishtei nashim hu de-mashkachat
lah. Since the only time when you get two boys and a
girl that the כהן Kohein gets nothing is the case of two
wives of two different husbands and one wife has already had kids,
באיש אחד ושתי נשים לא משכחת לה, be-ish echad u-shetei nashim lo
mashkachat lah, you wouldn't have it if they're both his wives. Why
if they're both his wives and you had two boys and a
girl, we do not have the same הלכה? Halacha? Because if they're
both his... wife and two boys and a girl, well one of
them, right is, well no wait, then one of them, why is
it true? Even if that's true, it could be that the one
that had never had kids had the girl first. Hold on a
second.
I guess it means that in the case of, oh, oh I'm
sorry, so we're going on the case of both wives, excuse me,
I'm sorry, we're going to the case where both wives had never
had kids. So if there's two husbands, two wives, both never had
kids, boy and a girl, you don't know whose is whose. So
the כהן Kohen gets nothing, right, because because
neither one, you can't prove that there's definitely a firstborn here but
you don't know which of them, which husband is obligated in it.
Okay, so if that's that case, so why didn't we give... now,
one minute, hold on a second.
And the ArtScroll comment doesn't make sense either.
Hold on a second. שבשתי נשים שבשני אנשים שלא בכרו וילדו שני
זכרים ונקבה כאן אין כאן לכהן כלום דחד אבי בכור וחד לאו
אבי בכור דאיכא למימר
האי פטור ואידך נמי פטור. she'beshtei nashim she'beshnei anashim shelo bicharu ve'yaldu
shnei zacharim u'nekeivah kan ein kan lakahen klum dechad avi bechor vechad
lav avi
bechor de'ika lemeimar
hai patur ve'idach nami patur. Right. No, I mean, it's true,
I mean, דאיכא חד פטור יהבי ליה לכהן להא לא תני לה.
de'ika chad patur yahavi leh lakahen leha lo
tani lah. Right.
So we're talking about, let's try this one more
time. So we're talking about זכר ונקבה אין כאן לכהן כלום. zachar
u'nekeivah ein kan lakahen klum.
We're talking about the case where there's let
me just check the note on the side one more time. אבות
פטורין. Avos peturin.
So we're talking about the case again where there's two wives, neither
of which have had kids before, and one has a boy, one
has a girl. So the כהן Kohen gets nothing because each husband,
two wives and two husbands, each husband says it's not my firstborn
son. Okay. Now תני רב הונא, tani Rav Huna, רב הונא Rav
Huna added to that case, שני זכרים ונקבה אין כאן לכהן כלום.
shnei zacharim u'nekeivah ein kan lakahen klum. It would also be true
if it was two boys and a girl, not just a boy
and a girl, because each one would say maybe my wife had
the girl first and therefore I don't have to give the כהן
Kohen anything. Okay, that's clear enough. Fine. ותנא דידן, ve'tana didan, why
did our Tanna not mention that? כיוון דבשני אנשים הוא דמשכחת לה.
keivan de'bishnei anashim hu de'meshkachas lah. That case about two boys and
a girl is true with two separate husbands that neither of them
have to give, because you don't know because each one will say
my wife had the girl first. באיש אחד ושתי נשים לא משכחת
לה. be'ish echad u'shtei nashim lo meshkachas lah. You don't have it
in one man and two wives. Why? Because with one man and
two wives, yes, one of them definitely had a boy first. One
of them definitely had a boy first. Right. One man and two
wives, one of them definitely had a boy first. So in that
case לא מתני לה, lo masni lah, it didn't give it, the
הלכה halacha would not be the same in that scenario. With two
separate wives, there is a בכור, bechor, you just don't know who,
so each is exempt. But with two wives of the same husband,
then then you definitely would have to give.
Oh wait, so he's disagreeing with רב הונא?
Rav Huna? No, he's just saying that's why we didn't give it
as an example because you don't have the exact parallel הלכה. halacha.
Of course, you don't have the parallel הלכה halacha in the case
of the boy and the girl either, because in the boy and
the girl, yeah, that's why I don't get it, because in the
boy and the girl, it's also different הלכה. halacha. If two separate
wives, neither father gives because each says it's my wife had the
girl first. But if they were both his wives, you would give.
So the הלכה halacha is
anyway asymmetrical regardless.
So I'm not exactly sure why we more told one case rather
than the other. All right, anyway, yes.
What? That the girl came out first? Yes. And the girl comes
out twice? Yes.
Then the boy is not a בכור. bechor. No. To whoever came
out first. Only if a boy came out first. Okay, let's go
on. Next משנה. mishnah. מת הבן בתוך שלשים יום אף על פי
שנתן לכהן יחזיר לאחר שלשים יום אף על פי שלא נתן יתן.
Meis haben betoch sheloshim yom af al pi she'nasan lakahen yachzir le'achar
sheloshim yom af al pi shelo nasan yiten.
So here is essentially the rule that was implicit in the previous
משנה. mishnah. The son died, God forbid, within 30 days. So even
if the money has been given to the כהן, Kohen, he has
to give it back because the מצוה mitzvah only begins on day
30, as we saw, you know, in all the earlier discussions, either
dying or the case of the father died, was there a lien
on the estate yet and so on. If he gave it after
30 days and then the son died, or he, I'm sorry, doesn't
really matter, he gave the money whenever he gave it, but the
son died after 30 days, then even if he hasn't given it,
אף על פי שלא נתן יתן. af al pi shelo nasan yiten.
Even though now this poor father doesn't have a son anymore, but
when day 30 came about he had a מצוה mitzvah to do
פדיון pidyon and even without and now even though his son has
died, that מצוה, mitzvah, that that is interesting. You might think that
the מצוה mitzvah begins on day 30, but it only exists as
long as there's still a live son who is obligated in פדיון.
pidyon. And we say no, once the son hit day 31, the
מצוה mitzvah applies even if afterwards the son has now died. He
became obligated to do that פדיון. pidyon. So it is not a
פדיון pidyon necessarily for a live and present child. תוספות Tosafot actually
asks a very sort of sad question. תוספות Tosafot says, imagine this.
First of all תוספות Tosafot says, you know, first of all he
says you make a ברכה שהחיינו bracha Shehecheyanu on פדיון, pidyon, not
on ברית מילה, bris milah, which is funny. All of the, you
know, all of the logic is you should make a שהחיינו Shehecheyanu
on ברית מילה. bris milah. ספרדי Sefardi make שהחיינו Shehecheyanu on ברית
מילה. bris milah. For some reason a practice developed amongst אשכנזי Ashkenazi
Jews not to make a שהחיינו Shehecheyanu on ברית מילה. bris milah.
Some try and it's a very people are really challenged to explain
why not. It could just be that there might have been a
lot of, one speculation is that there was a lot of infant
mortality. So maybe in anticipation of that possibility they didn't. It's hard
to understand why they didn't make a שהחיינו Shehecheyanu on ברית מילה.
bris milah. What?
They wouldn't do it when the kid was born either then but
that's not the practice.
Right. Right. Well, that's an interesting point actually. That we don't find,
you're right. If anything, that would be an argument not to say
it when the child was born and that we don't find them
saying. We only find them saying not to make it for ברית
מילה. bris milah. So maybe that, so maybe they, yeah. So anyway,
people really struggle to find a good explanation for that. Some say
because the child suffers some pain during the ברית מילה, bris milah,
but in general that's not seen as a legitimate reason not to
make a שהחיינו Shehecheyanu anyway. That's the practice of אשכנזים. Ashkenazim. תוספות
Tosafot says you do make a שהחיינו Shehecheyanu for פדיון הבן pidyon
haben because פדיון הבן pidyon haben is less frequent than kids. I
guess if you're having kids every year or two maybe it's not
considered such a שהחיינו, Shehecheyanu, although even things that are just seasonal
you make a... anyway he says you make a שהחיינו Shehecheyanu פדיון
הבן. pidyon haben. And then he imagines what would be the terrible
situation in this case, the son is dead and you're still doing
the מצוה mitzvah פדיון הבן pidyon haben and you're still making the
ברכה bracha and making a שהחיינו Shehecheyanu on the מצוה mitzvah of
פדיון הבן pidyon haben even though this child is dead. Someone made
a שהחיינו? Shehecheyanu?
He
says you probably would but he points out the sort of sad
irony of that case. Anyway, so that's what you do, you still
do the פדיון הבן. pidyon haben. אמר רב גידל, Amar Rav Gidel,
מת ביום שלשים. mes be'yom shloshim.
Now
how about day thirty? When does the מצוה mitzvah kick in? Day
thirty or day thirty-one? מת ביום שלשים כיום
שלפניו. mes be'yom shloshim ke'yom shelefanav. That's like the previous day, meaning
when it says מבן חדש, miben chodesh, a month old, mean he's
in his second month. Okay so thirty days are over and he
has begun day thirty-one, he's in his second month. That's what we
say. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, אם נתן לא יטול. im
nasan lo yital. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva isn't so sure the status
of day thirty. He says אם נתן לא יטול, im nasan lo
yital, if you gave already the money you can't take it back
if he died on day thirty because day thirty might already be
considered to be a month old. ואם לא נתן, ve'im lo nasan,
if the father hasn't given, לא יתן, lo yitein, he doesn't have
to give. So he's not certain whether day thirty is considered yet
a month old or not, so therefore whoever has the money gets
to keep it in this sad case where the son dies on
day thirty. Okay let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. What? Such a good way to give the money, you should
wait.
Well that's, yeah, that's sort of the lesson about all this right?
Why is the father running to do it? And we're going to
see in the next משנה mishnah in the discussion in the גמרא
Gemara that there's even limited scenarios where it might even, where it
will work even if the son does live. So anyway let's see
the גמרא. Gemara. מאי טעמא דרבנן? Mai tama de'rabbanan? What's the reason
of the rabbis?
גמירי חדש חדש ממדבר. Gemiri chodesh chodesh mimisbar. They learn out from
when they count in the beginning of במדבר, Bamidbar, it says מבן
חדש ומעלה, miben chodesh vama'alah, that you should count them from a
month and above. So the word and above, although really it just
means plus cases of older than a month, is used
to basically based on that word we understand that the month means
more than a month old. More than a month old means starting
on day thirty-one. Okay so that phrase and above.
So therefore that clearly starts on day thirty-one. מהתם ומעלה אף הכא
נמי ומעלה. Mahasam umalah af hacha nami umalah. Here it says מבן
חדש. miben chodesh. So we understand it's the same like over there,
it means starting on day thirty-one in the second month. רבי עקיבא
מספקא ליה. Rabbi Akiva mistakleih. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is not so
sure. מדאיצטריך למכתב ומעלה, mide'itztrich lemichtav umalah, since it had to say
and above by the counting in the beginning of במדבר, Bamidbar,
גבי ערכין gabei erchin ולא גמיר ממדבר, velo gmir mimisbar, it also
says, what does it say, a month and above when it talks
about ערכין, erchin, about how much you pay if you say this
person's ערך erech is on me and the תורה Torah gives a
chart, male or female, how old, one month, five years, and so
on. And there it also says a month and above. So why
did it have to say and above by ערכין? erchin? Why didn't
we just learn it out from the word, from the word month
in the context of the counting in the מדבר? Midbar? So since
it has to say it there ולא גמיר ממדבר, velo gmir mimisbar,
and the case of ערכין erchin did not learn it out from
the case of the counting in the wilderness, הוי להו שני כתובים
הבאים כאחד וכל שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין. havei leu shnei
kesuvim habayim ke'echad vechol shnei kesuvim habayim ke'echad ein melamdin. It's two
פסוקים pesukim that are coming to tell you the same thing and
the general rule is when they come to tell you the same
thing we understand that they're exceptions not the rule. If they were
the rules you would only have to say it once. If you
have to say it twice it means that they're exceptions. So maybe
the case there of the counting in the wilderness and the counting
for ערכין, erchin, maybe those are the exception and not the rule
and therefore the normal rule is that you start, day thirty is
already considered a month old, not day thirty-one. או דלמא, O dilma,
that's one possibility. Or do we say כי אין מלמדין לעלמא, ki
ein lelamdin le'alma, when do you not apply those two cases to
other unrelated cases? אבל לגופייהו מלמדין. aval legufaieu melamdin. But for their
own sake you do apply it. And why is this לגופייהו, legufaieu,
their own sake? Because, one minute, because,
hold on, because.
Right, because the בכור bechor in, oh, because over there, right, right.
Because in the beginning of במדבר, Bamidbar, when it says count from
a month and above, they were counting the בכורים, bechorim, right, they
were counting the firstborn in order to redeem them with the כהנים.
kohanim. Right, if you remember, right, the normal counting in the beginning
of במדבר, Bamidbar, right, is from twenty and above. Right, do we
have a חומש Chumash here? The normal counting in the beginning of
במדבר, Bamidbar, how does במדבר Bamidbar start? במדבר סיני
באהל מועד...
Bamidbar Sinai be-ohel moed...
מבן עשרים שנה ומעלה, mi-ben esrim shanah va-malah, right? So the normal
counting is from twenty years and above. Why did they do a
counting from a month above? They were counting the firstborns in order
to do the whole ritual of redeeming them and exchanging them with
the לוויים. Leviim. So, okay,
maybe we can't apply the principle of starting on day thirty-one to
other cases, but that was a case of redeeming the firstborn. It
wasn't our מצוה mitzvah of redeeming the firstborn, that was a special
ritual that was done once in the wilderness. But maybe that can
serve as the model for us. So therefore, do we say אבל
לגופיהו מלמדין, aval legufaiahu melamdin, for a similar sort of own, a
similar הלכה halakha you can apply it. And this is a similar
הלכה halakha to the case that existed already in the מדבר. midbar.
ומשום הכי מספקינן להו, u-mishum hachi misapkinan lehu, and therefore he doesn't
know how to treat day thirty-one, to treat it as less or
to treat it as day thirty, to treat it as under a
month or to treat it as a month. Now I want to
point out two things before we get to the אבעיא ibaya of
the גמרא. Gemara. One is, it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara assumes
that day thirty is a month, since the normal month is twenty-nine
and a half days. You know, it sort of assumes, you know,
you could have said that's, okay, it says בן חודש, ben chodesh,
but how do you know, meaning the only question is that day
thirty is the last day of the month, does that already count
as sort of the next day following? But it never sort of
seems to have a doubt whether you consider a month to be
twenty-nine or thirty. You always round up, because an average month is
always more than twenty-nine, you're always rounding up, and therefore the only
question is given that a month is thirty, how do you count
the last day? That being said, there's an interesting discussion in the
later פוסקים poskim about whether you would count, whether if you could
time it to the minute, whether you could do it after thirty
24-hour days, not just after, you know, day thirty, you know, and
now it's the next הלכתי halakhic day, but what would you do
after thirty 24-hour days, and can you do a פדיון הבן pidyon
haben at that time as well? And there's an interesting debate in
the פוסקים poskim about that. And Michael's going to say what's the
הלכה. halakha. Okay, so anyway, now let's at least look at what
the הלכה halakha is in the discussion in the גמרא. Gemara. אמר
רבא הכל מודים לעניין אבילות, amar Rava hakol modim le-inyan aveilus,
everybody would agree when it would come to אבילות, aveilus, because the
הלכה halakha is that a person, again God forbid here Bobby, you
should be appreciative of this because now we're actually introducing the fact
that when this tragedy happens, you know, there's an aspect of אבילות.
aveilus. Although interestingly and sadly or whatever, but anyway, if it is
a miscarriage or if the child dies less than thirty days old,
the גמרא Gemara has two understandings. The גמרא Gemara says has a
case where you know it was a full-term baby. If you know
it was a full-term baby, then even if it dies on day
one, then it's still considered like a full, it was considered viable,
if you know it was full-term, it dies, you sit שבעה, shiva,
all of the הלכות. halakhot. However, if there was a question whether
it was a full-term baby, then you need to survive the first
month in order to determine that it was viable. So in those
cases where it was a question whether it was a full-term baby
and it died within the first month, the parents would not sit
שבעה. shiva. You would treat it like a miscarriage. You would say
it was never viable. That's if it was uncertain if it was
full-term. Let's say in that case the child died on day thirty.
If it died on day thirty-one, you know that it's considered to
have been viable and sit שבעה. shiva. Day twenty-nine, you don't consider
it to be viable, don't sit שבעה. shiva. What happens if it
dies on day thirty? So he says הכל מודים לעניין אבילות, hakol
modim le-inyan aveilus, everybody would agree when it would come to אבילות,
aveilus, יום שלושים כיום שלפניו, yom shloshim ke-yom she-le-fanav, that it's like
that even רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who says that thirty here might
be considered old enough for פדיון הבן pidyon haben would say that
it would not, parents would not sit שבעה. shiva. Why? דאמר שמואל
הלכה כדברי המיקל באבל. de-amar Shmuel halakha ke-divrei ha-meikel be-avel.
We always go by the lenient opinion. So since even רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva himself says I don't know how to treat day thirty,
he would agree that when it came to אבילות aveilus perspective we'd
adopt the more lenient. When it came to other things, so then
maybe we would deal with the ספק safek and maybe actually you
could have a scenario in theory where the parents would give or
the כהן kohen at least would keep the money for פדיון הבן
pidyon haben and nevertheless they wouldn't sit שבעה shiva because they would
have to assume for אבילות הלכות aveilus halakhot assume that it was
not viable, but maybe come to a different conclusion for פדיון הבן
הלכות. pidyon haben halakhot. Yes, you would not say the ברכה. beracha.
Maybe not say the ברכה, beracha, that's an interesting question too according
to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, not say the ברכה, beracha, right. It
also raises an interesting question whether they're the same הלכה. halakha. Is
the reason that you wait till day thirty-one for פדיון הבן pidyon
haben for this viability issue or is it because no, the תורה
Torah just says מבן חודש? mi-ben chodesh? Now you know, now רש״י
Rashi actually on our משנה mishnah mentions... The reason less than thirty
days you don't do פדיון Pidyon is the child was miscarried and
a נפל Neifel wasn't viable. But תוספות Tosfos says that's wrong. That's
not the real logic because the logic because even if it was
definite full term and there's no concern of its viability and let's
say you know it was totally healthy and everything and who knows
God forbid a building fell on it had nothing to do with
its viability. If you knew it was full term you would do
then you know that's not what the issue is. The issue is
not about it being viable or not viable. The issue is that
the מצוה Mitzva doesn't begin until day 30. Once that's true that
conceptually it's different. There's a thirty day wait to determine viability when
you're not certain it was full term and then there's a separate
הלכה Halakha that even if you know it was completely viable the
מצוה Mitzva of פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen doesn't start until it's a
month old. So therefore it's not necessarily a contradiction. You could say
that there's we take one position in terms of viability right in
terms of and another position in terms of the מצוה Mitzva of
פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen right because they are they might follow different
laws. The פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen the thirty day demand is for
just that's when the מצוה Mitzva starts. It's not necessarily a function
of the thirty day wait to determine viability. Do you understand the
point I'm making? They're different areas of הלכה. Halakha. So we might
say that when it comes for viability we're going to be lenient
and when it comes for אבילות Aveilus and so on we're going
to assume a child isn't viable until he he's into day 31
whereas when it comes to the מצוה Mitzva of פדיון הבן Pidyon
HaBen it's not necessarily just oh it's a ספק Safek and we're
מחמיר Machmir both ways or מקיל Meikil both ways or whatever. No.
מצות פדיון הבן Mitzvas Pidyon HaBen is not about viability and therefore
the מצוה Mitzva begins maybe you know even on day 30 not
on day 31. So I just want to point out there's different
conceptual models here. It's not necessarily פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen is a
function about viability. They tell a story actually I just have to
mention in this context where you know somebody you know he had
a baby boy and he made a huge סעודת פדיון הבן Seudas
Pidyon HaBen you know whatever spent thousands of dollars and then you
know at at the meal he asks the rabbi to go up
to get up and say a few words and the rabbi says
it'd be my honor he says but I just want to right
understand like you know why did you make like such a huge
you know thing for the פדיון הבן? Pidyon HaBen? Normally it's like
out of proportion to what we normally do and he says well
I did it for my first son I figured I should do
it for my second son.
So then the rabbi gets up and says I want to wish
the אבי הבן Avi HaBen מזל טוב Mazel Tov on his son
no longer being a ספק נפל. Safek Neifel.
So that's bringing those two הלכות Halakhos together. Yes Michael.
I was just trying to understand are we saying that even if
it was like a full term baby that you don't do
You do not do פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen until day 31. Correct.
But I thought in terms of viability I thought that if it's
a בן שמונה Ben Shmona it's always considered not viable and if
it's a full term it's you just have to wait the thirty
days.
No if it's definite full term then it's first even from the
first day it's viable. If it's a doubtful full term you don't
know if it was full term or non-full term that's when you
need the thirty day wait. Okay. All right let yes.
Bobby class. Yes. Excuse me. Yes.
Yeah
I think I mean we recognize the word we're engaged in is
categorizing and characterizing and investigating these cases
but isn't it also you know it occurs to me that the
question of viability so if you
have a
question. Oh usual. Yes. When you oh I have a question afterwards
actually.
Okay fine. All right since we are already getting more behind. No
I accept let's go. We will ask after.
I want to know what a Bobby class is.
We're going to be finishing we're going to
be finishing מסכת Masechet in a month. Please please let's let's turn
the page. מת אביו תוך שלושים. Meis Aviv Toch Shloshim. Okay now
the father died the father died before day 30 and the son
wants to know he grows up and he never know he doesn't
know did my father ever do a פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen on
me? He died less than thirty. Now we've just learned it's possible
to give the money before day 30 but he doesn't know if
he did. בחזקת שלא נפדה. Be-Chezkas She-Lo Nifda. He should assume he
has not been redeemed. It would be highly unlikely although we've been
assuming those talking about those scenarios it would be highly unlikely that
a father would do a פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen before day 30
and therefore the son should assume not and he would have to
redeem himself. עד שיביא ראיה שנפדה. Ad She-Yavi Re'aya She-Nifda.
Unless he can give proof bring proof that he has been redeemed.
It questions about what type of proof would have there were witnesses
to the fact or something like that but otherwise he should he
has to assume he's not and he has to give five שקלים.
Shekalim.
What kind of ראיה? Re'aya?
There could be witnesses that that were at the פדיון הבן Pidyon
HaBen you know at the event. Okay. לאחר שלושים יום בחזקת שנפדה.
Le-Achar Shloshim Yom Be-Chezkas She-Nifda.
If he the father died after 30 days then he has to
assume that there was a פדיון הבן. Pidyon HaBen. Okay it's clear
from the גמרא Gemara it's not like they made a big סעודה
Seuda like I just said on day 31 or whatever and everybody
was invited etc. you know it's not so clear whether maybe he
waited a month or two before doing the פדיון. Pidyon. But no
anyway he died after after 30 days 31 days you assume the
father did the מצוה Mitzva at an early opportunity and he can
assume that he has been redeemed. עד שיאמרו לו שלא נפדה. Ad
She-Yomru Lo She-Lo Nifda. People tell him that he has not been
redeemed. And רש"י Rashi says why... יאמרו לו yomru lo as opposed
to יביא ראיה yavi ra-ayah because what type of a proof do
you bring about absence of something? And even if a כהן Kohen
says, I never got the money from your father, it's very nice
you never got the money from your father, right? Exactly.
So רש"י, Rashi, so what is the case of יאמרו לו? yomru
lo? So then how then? So רש"י Rashi says the case is
that people say that your father told us on his deathbed, you
know, that he never redeemed you. Some scenario like that, but it's
not exactly direct evidence because you can't have direct evidence really about
the absence of something.
The כהן Kohen since died who got the check.
Well, that's true too. Okay, now הוא לפדות, Hu lifdot, now we
have a very interesting... remember we spoke yesterday about whether the מצוה
mitzvah if the father dies and then the son is obligated, is
the son's מצוה mitzvah about himself derived from the father or is
it really his own מצוה mitzvah to redeem himself, right? Or the
other way, when we say the father redeems the son, is it
fundamentally the father's מצוה mitzvah or is the father doing it for
the son because the son can't do it for himself, but at
some conceptual level the son is obligated to redeem himself? So we've
been assuming it's fundamentally the father's obligation and if the father dies
the son's obligation is sort of, you know, is derived from his
father's obligation even for himself. So now here's the following
scenario: הוא לפדות ובנו לפדות. Hu lifdot u-beno lifdot. He has... he's
never been redeemed and now he has his own first-born son. Maybe
now people... you know, this actually does happen sometimes. People say, oh
you gotta do a פדיון. Pidyon. Really? I don't know if my
father ever did a פדיון. Pidyon. And then he realizes that he's
never had a פדיון Pidyon done for him. Okay, now who does
he do first? Okay, and so what... so הוא קודם לבנו. Hu
kodem li-beno. He takes care of himself before his son, which seems
to be saying that his מצוה mitzvah to redeem himself is the
primary one, and his son is only sort of, you know, maybe
he's doing the... he's doing it for his son, but ultimately a
person is primarily obligated for themselves. That's at least conceptually what it
sounds like. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda Omer: no, בנו קודמו. beno
kodmo. His son comes first before him, שמיצוותו על אביו. she-mitzvato al
aviv. The מצוה mitzvah to redeem the son is the father's מצוה.
mitzvah. It's not the person... it's not the child's מצוה. mitzvah. It's
the father's מצוה. mitzvah. So you have your... your primary מצוה mitzvah
is to redeem your son. ומיצוותו, u-mitzvato, excuse me, I know I
got that wrong, ומיצוותו, u-mitzvato, your מצוה, mitzvah, your redemption was your
father's מצוה. mitzvah. You're only getting it now by... you're deriving it,
but it's not primarily yours, it was primarily his. ומיצוות בנו, u-mitzvot
beno, but your son... to redeem your son is עליו, alav, that's
your primary מצוה. mitzvah. So therefore your obligation to your son comes
before your obligation to yourself. Sounds like a general rule about parenting.
Yeah, but let's say... let's say your father dies and then you
realize he never had a פדיון. Pidyon. Is there any obligation on
you?
No, I think
that's
the Mormons.
Yeah, but no,
no. There is a question about...
there is a question about whether like בברית מילה bi-berit milah we
definitely say that the מצוה mitzvah reverts to the larger community. There's
a question whether we say that at all by פדיון הבן Pidyon
HaBen or we don't. So if there is... if it is possible,
then it would not be the obligation of the son, then it
would just be the general community's obligation, you know, to do some
פדיון Pidyon for him. But in general the assumption... in general the
inclination is that it's not like בכור, bechor, that it basically is
on the father or on the son and it doesn't revert to
the mother or the community or anybody else.
You don't say like, you know, sort of like
מצוה בממון mitzvah be-mamon or something?
No, let's say the father didn't take לולב ואתרוג, Lulav ve-Etrog, you
know? So he's dead, then you understand and now he's dead, so
the מצוה mitzvah not necessarily.
By מילה milah more definitely because there's the objective reality that the...
that the son is not נימול. nimol. But don't you have to
give anything?
What? Right? If the father died not having had a...
that is... that is that question. Look, I'll just say very briefly,
this really comes up because in all of these cases about... about
where the father dies and the son has to redeem himself, the
big question is who's going to remember? Like 13 years from now,
who's going to remember that the son hasn't redeemed himself? So the
אחרונים Acharonim talk about writing, like making some jewelry in a bracelet
for him that basically says like בכור bechor or, you know, אינו
פדוי. eino paduy. And then then he'll wear it regularly and then
they'll look at it when he's 13 years old and they'll realize,
oh my God, we gotta do a פדיון הבן. Pidyon HaBen. But,
you know, do we... you know, it's questionable that's really going to
be a system that works. So the question becomes: can we as
a בית דין Beit Din be...
do a פדיון Pidyon for him even though he's a minor? And
therefore let's just take care of it now. And the issue there
is number one, even as a minor, well maybe we can make
a שליח shaliach for him because it's in his own interest. So
even though he's not an adult yet and can't appoint a שליח,
shaliach, we can appoint one for him. That would be one question.
Or even if he can't make a שליח shaliach because he is
a minor, but maybe as a... as a community we can take
on the responsibility of פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen and do it for
him. And that is very heavily debated in the פוסקים Poskim whether
you can do that, and I shall tell you that it really
comes up in cases of...
artificial insemination because artificial insemination now you know somebody had artificial insemination
had a firstborn baby boy so look nobody is going to pay
attention if you don't do a פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen like nobody's
taking you know is taking first of all there's C-sections there could
be miscarriages that precede nobody you know the absence of a פדיון
הבן Pidyon HaBen is not a בזיון Bizayon or whatever that you
have to do something you know now because otherwise people will wonder
but even that being said you know you're afraid you're going to
forget and artificial insemination happens more frequently nowadays than you know we
would imagine so what do you do in those cases you wait
till his בר מצוה Bar Mitzvah or do you do a פדיון
הבן Pidyon HaBen now and according to some פוסקים Poskim you do
a פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen now and you get a בית דין
Beis Din and the בית דין Beis Din makes the father you
know the wife's the mother's husband not the biological father makes him
their שליח Shliach so he's doing it not as a father but
as a representative of the בית דין Beis Din and or of
the son to do the פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen now just in
case you don't know if the donor has had a firstborn is
that what you're saying what's the case exactly I don't see
A not Jewish B questions about if the sperm donor is at
all considered the father so let's just assume not so the point
about this being that all these cases of the son redeeming himself
is do you wait till he's 13 or do you try to
take care of it now and the ability to take care of
it now depends on two possibilities either that you can appoint the
שליח Shliach for the son even though he's underage or the possibility
that it's the community's responsibility
okay but you don't say that in the case of the just
because just to wrap up my question you don't say that in
the case of the father dies without having had a פדיון Pidyon
the son doesn't have to do anything we don't
say it's the
community's obligation we don't say it's like
you know nice for the father right because here there's definitely an
obligation but we're afraid we're going to forget about it so we
might try to deal with it in this case but in general
we're not going to be חושש Choshesh that it's the community's obligation
as we've seen if there's no civil case then there's no we
don't do the מצוה Mitzvah just to play safe
yes what if the woman is artificially inseminated with her husband's sperm
would there be right keep it up yeah
so
that is an interesting question and there it goes to the question
whether in case of sperm donor thank you is the sperm donor
the biological considered halachically the father and just in a standard case
we don't know who it is and it's most likely a non-Jew
and so on or do we say that once it's done through
sperm that the sperm donor is not considered the biological father since
it but it's an interesting question because yeah no no but it
could be that it's an interesting question because one of the reasons
the sperm donor might not be considered the halachically the father might
not apply in the case where a man is donating his own
sperm for his wife so that's a very good question but there's
definitely much more reason to think there that we would fully consider
the father the father okay yeah
could you say what if the father died and people said afterwards
that he said that
there was never a פדיון Pidyon the son's not obligated because people
witnesses say
no if he said there was never a פדיון Pidyon the son
is obligated
if witnesses said
that the father said on his deathbed that he had never done
it then the son is obligated okay let's take a look at
the גמרא Gemara איתמר Itmar הפודה את
בנו בתוך שלשים יום
HaPodeh Es Beno Besoch Shloshim Yom
so this is the case of our משנה Mishnah but now we're
going to see it's debated what parameters it works you gave the
פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen within 30 days remember the מצוה Mitzvah does
not begin until day 31 so how could you do the מצוה
Mitzvah before the time so רב אמר בנו פדוי Rav Amar Beno
Paduy it still works ושמואל אמר אין בנו פדוי U'Shmuel Amar Ein
Beno Paduy it doesn't work דכולי עלמא Dechulei Alma now the גמרא
Gemara clarifies everybody agrees מעכשיו אין בנו פדוי Me'achshav Ein Beno Paduy
if you said I'm giving it today on day two or day
eight or day ten and I want it to work today then
everybody says it doesn't work the מצוה Mitzvah doesn't begin yet it
can't work today now what do you do with the money is
an interesting question do we assume the money was a gift or
do we assume the money you have to give back but that's
not our discussion right now okay but if you tried to do
it right now everybody agrees it doesn't work מעכשיו אין בנו פדוי
Me'achshav Ein Beno Paduy לאחר שלשים יום Le'achar Shloshim Yom if you
say I'm giving you the money now so that on day 31
it will take effect the פדיון Pidyon will take effect now ואינהו
המעות Ve'isnu HaMaos if the money is still around at that day
ודאי בנו פדוי Vadai Beno Paduy everybody agrees it works because the
כהן Kohen has the money you said it'll take effect now it's
like you gave me the money now so therefore everybody agrees that
if the money is still around it works כי פליגי Ki Peligi
here's the debate לאחר שלשים יום ונתאכלו
המעות Le'achar Shloshim Yom Venisachlu HaMaos you say it'll take effect after
30 days and when 30 days or 31 days rolls around the
money has already been spent so in that case okay can you
do the act now with the effect to take place later or
because if the money is still around it's like the act was
done later if the money isn't around then the act is being
done now with the effect being postponed can you do that or
not okay רב אמר בנו פדוי Rav Amar Beno Paduy it it
does work מידי דהוה אקידושי אשה Mididi Hava AKiddushei Isha just like
if a person marries a woman and he says here's this ring
and I will marry you and the marriage will take effect 30
days from now the act is done now but the effect takes
place later so if it can work there it can work here
התם לאו אף על גב דנתאכלו המעות Hasam Lav Af Al Gav
Denisachlu HaMaos there we say even if the money's already been spent
הוו קידושין Hava Kiddushin it works הכא נמי לא שנא Hacha Nami
Lo Shenei here too it would be no different. And Shmuel said
to you, Shmuel would say back, התם בידו לקדשה מעכשיו. Hasam beyado
lekadsha meachshav. There he could have done it today. He just chose
to make it take effect 30 days from now. So the fact
that he could have done it today, he's empowered to split the
act and the effect because he could have had the kiddushin take
effect right now. So therefore he's sort of, you know, in control
of it and therefore he can say, I'll do the act now
and the effect, rather than the way it would naturally happen now,
I will define that the effect of the kiddushin will take place
later. That I accept. הכא אין בידו לפדותו מעכשיו. Hacha ein beyado
leifdoso meachshav. Here he can't do the pidyon now. So if he
can't do the pidyon now, I can't even call it the act
being done now. He's not in control. He doesn't, he can't control
the effect. He can't make it take place now. Maybe it's not
even an act of pidyon now. So no, you don't even get
started less than 30 days and therefore you cannot split the act
from the effect. And so, that's, that's the debate. So Shmuel makes
a pretty cogent argument. And now the Gemara says, this sounds like
a later gloss because here's what the Gemara says, it like even
interrupts the whole flow and it we're going to see repeats itself.
ואף על גב דקיימא לן, Ve-af al gav de-kaima lan, even though
we normally hold דכל היכא דפליגי רב ושמואל הלכתא כרב באיסורי וכשמואל
בדיני, de-chol hacha de-pleigi Rav u-Shmuel hilchasa ke-Rav be-isuri u-ke-Shmuel be-dinei, we
rule like Rav when it comes to, whenever they debate, we rule
like Rav when it comes to sort of issues of mitzvos and
issur ve-heter and we rule like Shmuel in civil cases. And therefore
you would think we go like Rav, הכא הלכתא כוותיה דשמואל. hacha
hilchasa kevasei de-Shmuel. Here we rule like Shmuel. Maybe his reasoning was
more cogent or just the consensus developed. Now it is interesting that
the Gemara does consider this in principle to be a case of
איסורי, isuri, not ממונא, mamona, since as we've been seeing, the question
of the mitzvah pidyon haben is a direct function of the דיני
ממונות dinei mamonos aspect of pidyon haben. So you could say maybe
that is why we rule like Shmuel. But that's not what it
sounds like. It sounds like this is really issur, but this is
an exception and we're going to rule like Shmuel here. Okay, now
let's take a look at what the Gemara says. It's going to
try to prove it from our Mishnah. תנן, Tenan, we taught in
our Mishnah, מת בתוך שלשים יום, Meis besoch shloshim yom, if he
died within 30 days, אף על פי שנתן לכהן יחזיר, af al
pi she-nassan la-kohen yachzir, even though he gave the money to the
Kohen, the Kohen has to give it back. חמש סלעים. Chamesh sela'im.
טעם, Ta'ama, the reason, דמת, de-meis, because the child died. So therefore
the whole thing was never took effect. הא לא מת, Ha lo
meis, if the child didn't die, בנו פדוי, beno fadui, it works
even though, right? That's basically true. All the Mishnahs we've been seeing
have been dealing with cases where the money was given within 30
days. So you see, so you see it works. So the Gemara
has an obvious answer, הכא מאי עסקינן דאיתנהו למעות. Hacha mai askinan
de-isnehu le-ma'os. No, Shmuel agrees it works if the money is around
on day 31. That's like the whole thing took place on day
31. So all the Mishnayot that assume that it can work if
you gave the money within 30 days are scenarios where the money
was still around on day
31. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear again, בחזקת שלא נפדה
עד שיביא ראיה שנפדה, be-chezkat she-lo nifdah ad she-yavi ra-ayah she-nifdah, it
says if the father dies within 30 days, you can assume that
he hasn't been redeemed. So but, I mean, but if you know
that he was, he did the mitzvah, then it would be good
even though the father died within 30 days. התם נמי דאיתנהו למעות
בעינייהו, Hasam nami de-isnehu le-ma'os be-eineihu, there too, we mean that there's
proof that he did the mitzvah in 30 days and that the
money is still around. Okay, so all these cases where it sounds
like it works within 30 days, according to Shmuel are scenarios where
the money is still around on day 31. תני תנא קמיה דרב
יהודה. Tani tanna kamei de-Rav Yehuda. So a Tanna taught in front
of Rav Yehuda, הפודה בנו בתוך שלשים יום בנו פדוי, ha-podeh beno
besoch shloshim yom beno fadui, that it works within, within 30 days.
Now remember, Rav Yehuda was a student of Shmuel. And he just
said straight, it works within 30 days. No qualification. So אמר ליה,
amar lei, he said to him, שמואל אמר אין בנו פדוי. Shmuel
amar ein beno fadui. Shmuel says it doesn't work within 30 days
under a standard case. ואת אמרת בנו פדוי? ve-at amart beno fadui?
And you're just telling me straight it's redeemed? You should have qualified
it, only if the money is around and so on. Because according
to Shmuel, if the money isn't around, it doesn't work if you
did it early. ואף על גב, Ve-af al gav, and now the
Gemara repeats itself, which again indicates that this might have been a
later gloss, ואף על גב דקיימא לן כרב באיסורי וכשמואל בדיני הלכתא
הכא כוותיה דשמואל. ve-af al gav de-kaima lan ke-Rav be-isuri u-ke-Shmuel be-dinei
hilchasa hacha kevasei de-Shmuel. We rule like Shmuel that if he did
it early and the money is not around, it does not work.
Okay, we're going to go to the Mishnah. If somebody has to
leave now, I understand, but we're just going to go to the
Mishnah. Yes.
There's an article footnote that says Rambam, Ramban, and Rosh rule according
to Rav.
They ignore this gloss? Yeah. Oh, that's interesting. I didn't check that
out. Okay. So they must really assume that this is a Geonic
gloss. Very often, the הלכתאs hilchasa in the Gemara were are not
originally in the Gemara, a lot of them were from הלכות גדולות.
Hilchos Gedolos. And because הלכות גדולות, Hilchos Gedolos, because it was written
in Aramaic and it follows the flow of the Gemara and it
just ends with a הלכתא, hilchasa, often what happened is the הלכתאs
hilchasa in הלכות גדולות Hilchos Gedolos were glossed back into the Gemara.
So,
so that's interesting. I did not check the פסק psak on that,
but that would, that would certainly re-reinforce just, you get a sense
just by the, you know, by the way it keeps on inserting
it and it does it twice, that this is really a later
gloss. But that's fascinating. Okay. So now the Gemara says like
this: הוא לפדותו ובנו לפדותו הוא קודם לבנו. hu lifdoso u-veno lifdoso
hu kodem li-veno. So this is the, again, this really interesting question
about you and your son where, it seems that the argument about
Rav Yehuda was very cogent, that your fundamentally your obligation is on
your son, not on yourself. But let's take a look at what
the Gemara says.
תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabanan: הוא לפדות ובנו לפדות, Hu lifdos u'vno lifdos,
it's between you and your son.
הוא קודם לבנו, Hu kodem livno, you come first. רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda אומר: omer, בנו קודמו. Bno Kodmo. No, your son comes first.
שמצותו על אביו, She'mitzvaso al aviv, your מצוה mitzvah was your father's
מצוה. mitzvah. ומצות בנו עליו, U'mitzvas bno alav, it's your son's מצוה
mitzvah עליו alav is your primary מצוה. mitzvah. So אמר רבי ירמיה,
Amar Rabbi Yirmeyah, הכל מודים היכא דליכא אלא חמש סלעים. Hakol modin
heicha d'leika ela chamesh sela'im. So now rather רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeyah
rather than leaving it as this very base, you know, seems principled
debate about whether it's fundamentally your מצוה, mitzvah, whether it's you know
your מצוה mitzvah is about yourself or your מצוה mitzvah is on
your son, sort of takes you know reframes it in the following
way. הכל מודים היכא דליכא אלא חמש סלעים. Hakol modin heicha d'leika
ela chamesh sela'im. Everybody agrees if you only have five סלעים. sela.
Until now by the way we were assuming that the question was
just what order you're doing it in. רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeyah says
it's not only a question of order, it might be only one
of them will get done, it might be you only have five
סלעים. sela. So then it's not just a question of order but
whose is it who're you going to do? So everybody agrees if
you only have five סלעים, sela, הוא קודם לבנו, Hu kodem livno,
you come first.
מאי טעמא דמצוה דידיה עדיף, Mai ta'ama d'mitzvah didei adif, your own
מצוה mitzvah is more important. Now what does that mean? Does that
mean that conceptually it's your מצוה mitzvah to be redeemed yourself and
when we say it's the father's מצוה mitzvah it means he's doing
it for his son? Or maybe we don't say that? Maybe we
actually say no no it's true, you have a מצוה mitzvah to
redeem your son, it's primarily your מצוה mitzvah and you have a
מצוה mitzvah to redeem yourself which derived from your father. We accept
it was primarily your father's and your מצוה mitzvah derived from your
father. But nevertheless you know you're sort of like the same way
we sort of
say like חייך וחיי אחיך חייך קודמין, Chayecha v'chayei achicha chayecha kodmin,
you know when it's sort of your life and somebody else's life
you have a responsibility first to take care of your own life.
So since this מצוה mitzvah relates to your own personal status of
have you been redeemed or not, even though it was derived from
your father's, you're allowed to take care of things that relate to
your status before you take care of things that relate to your
son's status. So that's a possible way of learning it. That it's
yeah.
It's also a question of קדימה kadima because you know you only
have five סלעים sela now but only next year you'll have another
five. Right. You know so then the מצוה mitzvah will still be
there for the other for the one you didn't do first.
Right but you never know cause a person might always be stuck
in poverty. But whether it's מצות קדימה, mitzvah kadima, whether it's מצוה
mitzvah of being happening or not, my question is when he says
everybody agrees that under normal circumstances you come first because your מצוה
mitzvah because because your מצוה mitzvah comes first. What does he mean
by the phrase your מצוה? mitzvah? Does he mean that the מצות
פדיון הבן mitzvah pidyon haben is fundamentally on the child and the
father is doing it for the child? Then fundamentally it is your
מצוה mitzvah and your son's doing your son is only taking care
of it for someone else or no? Maybe we can agree that
fundamentally it's your מצוה mitzvah for your son and your מצוה mitzvah
on yourself is only derivative but nevertheless since it relates to your
status you're entitled to take care of things that relate to your
status before you take care of things that relate to your son's
status. So two very different ways of framing what he means. Anyway
let's see how he explains this debate. אימת פליגי, Eimas pligi, when
did they
debate היכא דאיכא חמש משועבדות וחמש בני חורין Heicha d'ika chamesh meshubados
v'chamesh bnei chorin that you have five שקל shekel that basically is
a field that you sold. And therefore
your
father was obligated to redeem you, he had a field, so there
was a five שקל shekel lien that the class כהנים kohanim had
on that field because when your father was alive and you were
a baby boy they had a right to that field. That field
now got sold to other people. Now you have five שקל shekel
hard cold cash. Okay so right now you understand if you go
if the for the father's מצוה mitzvah for for the מצוה mitzvah
of redeeming you the father's מצוה mitzvah you could go to the
field because there was a lien on it. There wasn't a lien
on when your son was born, you didn't have that field in
your possession. So there you can only get the cash for the
son, the כהן kohen has no rights to the field which wasn't
in your possession when the son was born. Okay so that's the
case. So in that case רבי יהודה סבר מלוה הכתובה בתורה ככתובה
בשטר דמיא Rabbi Yehuda savar milveh hakesuvah ba'Torah k'kesuvah b'shtar damya that
the fact that the מצות פדיון mitzvah pidyon is written in the
תורה Torah is like it's written in a שטר shtar and therefore
there is a lien on the field that was sold, that's what
we talked about yesterday. And therefore ודידיה אזיל וטרי ממשעבדי. V'didei azil
v'tari m'meshubadei. So your פדיון pidyon what your father should have done,
there was a lien on it. So fine let them go and
collect from that lien, they're entitled to from my father's מצוה. mitzvah.
And for my and now my redeeming from my son, my מצוה
mitzvah I'll give him the cash.
Okay so that's why he says that
your son comes first meaning you use your cash for your son
because they can always go and use the lien for the for
the מצוה mitzvah of your redemption. ורבנן סברי, V'Rabanan savri,
the rabbis held מלוה הכתובה בתורה לאו ככתובה בשטר דמיא. Milveh hakesuvah
ba'Torah lav k'kesuvah b'shtar damya. No, there was no lien on that
property because the obligation to pay did not create a lien, it's
not like it's written on a document. So you only have five
שקל shekel for you or your son and you have to choose
between the two, there's no way they're both going to get done,
at least not now. So therefore הלכך מצוה דידיה עדיף, Hilkach mitzvah
didei adif, you come first. And again so bracketing the interesting question
about the lien. In my mind the more interesting question is how
do we conceptualize the מצוה mitzvah of and it's the same question
about ברית מילה. bris milah. Do we say fundamentally it's the son's
מצוה mitzvah but the father does it for the son? Or do
we say fundamentally it's the father's מצוה? mitzvah? רב יהודה Reb Yehuda
was very clear. רב יהודה Reb Yehuda said at least the way
he was phrased in the משנה, Mishnah, fundamentally it's the father's מצוה.
mitzvah. But the רב ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya says no no no everybody
would agree that if all things being equal you come first. So
is it because he's saying that we basically say it's your מצוה
mitzvah to redeem yourself? Or no, it is your father's מצוה mitzvah
but because it's about your status you're allowed to take care of
your own needs before you take care not necessarily your own מצוה
mitzvah but your own needs in terms of your status of being
unredeemed you're allowed to take care of that before you take care
of issues relating to your son. Okay, to be continued tomorrow. Thank
you. Appreciate it. Yes, I apologize.
Yes, I apologize.